Guide to the Oakland Methodist Episcopal Church Records, 1872-1933 AIS.1997.39
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Oakland Methodist Episcopal Church Records
1872-1933
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Oakland Methodist Episcopal Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1997.39
1 microfilm_reel
The Oakland Methodist Episcopal Church was an active church in Pittsburgh's East End from 1878-1934. The Church eventually merged and is known currently as the First United Methodist Church of Pittsburgh. The records consist of six books, which have been microfilmed, that contain the records of members, pastors, baptisms, marriages, probationers, including the Church's history for the years 1872-1933.
History
The Oakland Methodist Episcopal Church began in 1869 or 1870 as a Sabbath School held in the Bellefield Public School Building on Fifth Avenue in Pittsburgh. The organizer of the gatherings was William B. Evans. The Church as a congregation was organized by D.L. Dempsey, presiding elder of the Pittsburgh District, and Reverend J.C. High, City Missionary, on January 10, 1872. In 1873 the Church purchased property at Forbes Avenue and Bouquet Street from Edward W. H. Schenley and prepared for construction. The Church was finished and dedicated in September, 1878.
In the early 1900s the Church became a Wesley Foundation Church and functioned as a social and religious center for students of the University of Pittsburgh. At one time the Church had a membership of 350 full members and 250 Sunday school members or probationers. The Great Depression of the 1930s affected the Church by decreasing its. High budget deficits caused the Methodist Official Board's recommendation to consolidate Oakland Methodist Episcopal Church with the Christ Methodist Episcopal Church in 1934. In 1968 Christ Methodist Episcopal Church merged with Evangelical United Brethren to become the First United Methodist Church of Pittsburgh which still functions today.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection consists of six books, which have been microfilmed, and contain the records of members, pastors, baptisms, marriages, probationers, and include the church's history for the years 1872-1933. Individuals in the membership records are listed alphabetically. Names in the marriage, baptismal, and pastoral records are listed in chronological order.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were microfilmed with the permission of the First United Methodist Church of Pittsburgh, PA in 1997.
Existence and Location of Copies
The originals are located in the archives of the First United Methodist Church.
Previous Citation
Oakland Methodist Episcopal Church Records, AIS.1997.39, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Oakland Methodist Episcopal Church, ais 97:39, Records, 1872-1933, Archives of Industrial Society, Hillman Library, University of Pittsburgh
Churches and Synagogues; Oakland (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- History; First United Methodist Church of Pittsburgh (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Oakland Methodist Episcopal Church (Pittsburgh, Pa.) -- Archives
- Volume I, 1872-1885; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Volume I contains a history of the church written in 1888, and lists of the church's probationers, classes, full members, pastors, statistics, baptisms, and marriages. All names are listed in chronological order except for the membership records which are arranged alphbetically. Probationer records contain the information of the individual's status, residence, member date, and gender. Class records are lists containing names of individuals enrolled in specific church classes. Pastoral records contain the name of the paster and dates served. Baptism and marriage records contain name, date, date of birth, parent names, residence, and place of birth.
  - Historical Record, 1872-1888 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Reel 1)
  - Probationers, 1872-1884
  - Class Records
  - Full Members, 1872-1885
  - Pastoral Statistical Records, 1872-1877
  - Baptism Records, 1872-1885
  - Marriage Records, 1872-1885
- Volume II, 1885-1900; II.
  Volume II contains lists of full members, probationers, marriages, and baptisms.
  - Full Members, 1885-1900
  - Probationers, 1886-1900
  - Marriage Records, 1886-1900
  - Baptism Records, 1885-1900
- Volume III, 1900-1904; III.
  Volume III contains lists of full members, probationers, marriages, and baptisms.
  - Probationers, 1901-1904
  - Full Members, 1900-1904
  - Baptism Records, 1901-1904
  - Marriage Records, 1900-1904
- Volume IV, 1904-1909; IV.
  Volume IV contains lists of full members, probationers, marriages, and baptisms.
  - Probationers, 1905-1909
  - Full Members, 1905-1909
  - Baptism Records, 1905-1909
  - Marriage Records, 1904-1909
- Volume V, 1909-1919; V.
  Volume V contains lists of full members, probationers, marriages, and baptisms.
  - Full Members, 1909-1918
  - Probationers, 1910-1919
  - Marriage Records, 1909-1918
  - Baptism Records, 1909-1919
- Volume VI, 1872-1933; VI.
  Volume VI contains a history of the church written in 1918 or 1919 and lists of full members, pastors, probationers, marriages, baptisms, and funeral records. The pastoral records contain names listed in chronological order.
  - Historical Record
  - Pastoral Records, 1872-1930
  - Records of Official Members, 1918
  - Probationers, 1919-1932
  - Baptized Children, 1919
  - Records of Full Members, 1876-1932
  - Baptism Records, 1904-1931
  - Marriage Records, 1919-1933
  - Funeral Records, 1919-1932